Finding Aid for Donald A. Johnston papers
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Donald A. Johnston papers 1979-2012 1989-2012
Johnston, Donald A., III
12.5 linear feet
2015029 Aa 2
Records of the professional career and judicial rulings of Donald A. Johnston III, judge on Michigan's 17th Circuit Court and former judge on the state's 61st District Court. Includes summaries of cases brought before Johnston for sentencing in the circuit court, the judge's notes on sentences levied in each case, files related to appellate court proceedings, and correspondence.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Donated by Judge Donald A. Johnston (donor no. 11268 ), in May 2015.
The Donald A. Johnston papers are open for research
Donald Allerton Johnston III was born February 25, 1944 in Norfolk, Virginia. He was the only child of Donald A. Johnston, Jr. (University of Michigan B.A., 1934) and Harriet M. (Wolfs) Johnston, who met as students at the University of Michigan. At the time of Donald A. Johnston III's birth, Donald A. Johnston Jr. served at the Little Creek Amphibious Base near Norfolk, VA. He was later shipped out for the Pacific and fought at Iwo Jima and Okinawa. After the War the family returned to Michigan, settling in Detroit and later residing in Birmingham. The future Judge Johnston graduated from Birmingham's Wylie E. Groves High School in 1962.
In 1966, Johnston earned a Bachelor of Arts degree in history from the University of Virginia. He subsequently pursued the study of law at Wayne State University, receiving a juris doctorate cum laude and with silver key in 1969. On June 2 of that year, Johnston began his legal career in West Michigan, joining the staff of the Kent County Prosecuting Attorney as a law clerk. His skillful handling of a high volume of trial and appellate cases later garnered Johnston the positions of Deputy Assistant Prosecuting Attorney and Chief Assistant Prosecuting Attorney; the first decade of his career also saw the future judge specialize in arguing cases before the Michigan Supreme Court. Johnston's campaign for Prosecuting Attorney in 1976, however, proved unsuccessful.
On February 19, 1979, Governor William G. Milliken appointed Johnston to a vacant judgeship in the 61st District Court in Grand Rapids. Judge Johnston was elected to a full term in 1980 and retained his post in the 1986 election. By vote of his district court colleagues, Johnston was selected as Chief Judge Pro Tempore in 1979; he served as the court's Chief Judge in 1980 and for four additional terms that decade.
When Judge Stuart Hoffius announced his retirement from Kent County's 17th Circuit Court in 1988, Judge Johnston ran successfully to replace him; he subsequently won reelection in 1994, 2000, 2006, and 2012. Assigned to the court's Criminal/Civil Division, Johnston served as Chief Judge Pro Tempore from 2004 to 2009; from 2010 to 2015, he held the post of 17th Circuit Court Chief Judge by appointment of the Michigan Supreme Court. In October 2015, Johnston was reappointed to this position for a two year term to commence January 1, 2016. During his tenure as Chief Judge, Johnston advocated for the addition of judges to the court to reduce overcapacity judicial workloads and expedite the resolution of cases, attempting to align his court more fully with state recommendations.
Judge Johnston extensively involved himself in professional development and organizations during his time on the bench. A member of numerous bar and judicial associations, he graduated from the National Judicial College and the Michigan Judicial Institute, serving on the faculty of the latter on several subsequent occasions. In his capacity as a member of the Michigan State Bar, he chaired its Standing Committee on Standard Criminal Jury Instructions. In 2011, Johnston began a term of service on Michigan's Council on Law Enforcement and Reinvention (CLEAR) by appointment of Governor Rick Snyder.
With his wife, the former Shaula Woodall, Judge Johnston has three adult children and four grandchildren.
The collection is divided into three series: Felony Sentencing Files, Appeals and Boot Camp Files, and Correspondence.
The Donald A. Johnston papers document extensively criminal court proceedings in Kent County, particularly between 1989 and 2012. A substantial breadth of materials pertaining to trials brought before Johnston for more than twenty years offer insight into crime rates, criminal law, and the nature of sentences levied against convicted persons in the greater Grand Rapids area. Documents in the Johnston files also follow the progress of trials later referred to appellate courts in Michigan, including both the Court of Appeals and the Michigan Supreme Court, as well as sentences with which Johnston disagreed. Finally, Johnston's correspondence captures the interactions of the judge with legal professionals and the public at large.
Subjects:
Court administration--Michigan.; Court administration--United States.; Johnston, Donald A., III, 1944-; Judges--Michigan--Kent County (Mich.); Kent County (Mich.); Michigan. Circuit Court (Kent County); United States. District Court (Michigan: Eastern District); Michigan Judicial Institute.
- Felony Sentencing Files
  Materials in the Felony Sentencing Files (7.5 linear feet) series derive from Johnston's tenure with the 17th Circuit Court, the court with the broadest range of trial powers in Kent County. Every case brought before the judge for sentencing between 1989 and 2012 appears to be represented in these files. Notably, materials in this series include Johnston's handwritten summaries of the defendants' crimes, his investigations into their existing criminal records, and the penalty to be levied, in accordance with Michigan sentencing guidelines. To expedite his preparation of these notes, Johnston crafted a form of shorthand referencing legal terms and Kent County locations; each box in the Felony Sentence Files series includes his explanation of the origin of the shorthand, a key to its abbreviations, and a brief description of the means by which he determines the sentence in each case.
  - Felony sentences, 1989-1992, 23 folders (Box 1)
  - Felony sentences, 1993-1996, 20 folders (Box 2)
  - Felony sentences, 1997-1999, 22 folders (Box 3)
  - Felony sentences, 2000-2003, 26 folders (Box 4)
  - Day sheets for trials and sentences, 2001-2004, 14 folders (Box 8)
  - Felony sentences, 2004-2007, 26 folders (Box 5)
  - Felony sentences, 2008-2011, 25 folders (Box 6)
  - Felony sentences, 2012, 7 folders (Box 7)
- Appeals and Boot Camp Files
  Documents in the Appeals and Boot Camp Files (3.0 linear feet) pertain to instances, generally criminal cases, in which the defendant requested review of a case in a court higher than the one in which his or her case was first tried or sentences in which the convicted requested clemency. Judge Johnston retained copies of opinions prepared by the Michigan Court of Appeals and the Michigan Supreme Court, and these materials offer insight into the process by which appellate courts reach their decisions, as well as explanations of the facts of each case. The series also includes uniquely valuable materials on Michigan's Special Alternative Incarceration (SAI) Boot Camps, established in 1988 to provide a productive, work-based program for those convicted of certain classes of crimes in the state. These papers primarily pertain to Judge Johnston's assent or objection to an SAI sentence for a given defendant. Finally, notices of requests for commutation in cases heard by Judge Johnston, related documents, and selections from the judge's responses to these pending hearings complete the series.
  - Court of Appeals and Michigan Supreme Court appeals decisions, 1990-2005, 21 folders (Box 9)
    (includes Kent County Prosecutor applicants, 1986)
  - Court of Appeals and Michigan Supreme Court appeals decisions, 2006-2012, 7 folders (Box 10)
  - SAI Boot Camp responses, 2006-2012, 1 folders (Box 10)
  - Commutation responses, 2009-2010, 2 folders (Box 10)
- Correspondence
  Papers in the Correspondence series (3.0 linear feet) largely stem from Judge Johnston's communication with others in a professional capacity. Organized chronologically by year of receipt, materials in this series include letters from lawyers, other judges, law school professors, newspapers, and professional judicial organizations of which Johnston was a member. A selection of the correspondence was also penned by citizens commending the judge's performance during their jury duty, crime victims or family members of victims praising the judge's sentences, and defendants petitioning for parole, objecting to their sentences, or appealing to Johnston for assistance while under sentence. Finally, a small portion of the series concerns Johnston's personal life, such as letters regarding membership in the Sons of the American Revolution.
  - 1979-1986, 10 folders (Box 11)
  - 1988-1999, 16 folders (Box 12)
  - 2000-2010, 15 folders (Box 13)
    (includes court notice of 2015 appointment as Chief Judge)
Related Material
Researchers interested in the judicial process in Michigan or in judges with ties to the state may also wish to consult the following collections held by the Bentley Historical Library:
Donald E. Aams papers
Theodore R. Bohn papers
James Ritchison Breakey papers
Harry T. Edwards papers
Albert Joseph Engel Jr. papers
Isaac P. Christiancy diplomatic dispatches and instructions
Glenn C. Gillespie papers
Lawrence M. Glazer papers
Benjamin F. Graves papers
Hoffius Family papers
Malcolm Keith Hatfield papers
Charles W. Joiner papers
Cornelia G. Kennedy papers
Arthur J. Lacy papers
Charles E. Lewis papers
John Wesley Longyear papers
Frank Murphy papers
Samuel D. Pepper papers
Frank A. Picard papers
Benjamin C. Stanczyk papers
Raymond Wesley Starr papers
Arthur J. Tuttle paper
Carl M. Weideman papers